A Guide to the Improved Benevolent and Protective Order of Elks of the World, Greater Capitol City Lodge, No. 11 (Richmond, Virginia), Records, 1907-1992
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Improved Benevolent and Protective Order of Elks of the World, Greater Capitol City Lodge, No. 11 (Richmond, Virginia), Records, 1907-1992
Library of Virginia
38098
3.6 cubic feet; 6 Hollinger boxes and 1 oversize box; box numbers 1-7
Improved Benevolent and Protective Order of Elks of the World, Greater Capitol City Lodge, No. 11 (Richmond, Virginia)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Membership applications are restricted until fifty years after their creation date (i.e. 1952 files may be accessed in the year 2002).
Acquisition Information
This collection was given to The Library of Virginia in April 2001 by the Improved Benevolent and Protective Order of Elks of the World, Greater Capitol City Lodge, No. 11, 526 North 2nd Street, Richmond, Virginia 23223.
Historical Information
The Improved Benevolent and Protective Order of Elks of the World was formed on 28 September 1898 in Cincinnati, Ohio, and is currently the largest African-American fraternal organization in the world. Known for providing social and financial services to member's families upon their untimely death, the organization also developed specific departments to address concerns related to education, health, veteran's affairs, and civil liberties. Members pay monthly dues and burial fund taxes. The Greater Capitol City Lodge was one lodge under the auspices of the Virginia State Association of the I.B.P.O.E.W., which itself was subordinate to the National Association of the I.B.P.O.E.W.
Scope and Content Information
Records, 1907-1992, of the Improved Benevolent and Protective Order of Elks of the World, Greater Capitol City Lodge, No. 11, an African-American fraternal organization located in Richmond, Virginia.
Arrangement
Arrangement
Materials arranged chronologically.
Organization
The collection is organized into the following series:
Series I: Correspondence
Series II: Financial records
Series III: Committee reports and files
Series IV: Minutes
Series V: Constitutions, by-laws, and charters
Series VI: Photographs and posters
Series VII: Publications
Series VIII: Membership files
Separated Materials
Related memorabilia from this collection was given to the Valentine Museum, 1015 East Clay Street, Richmond, Virginia, 23219.
Contents List
- Correspondence 1975-1991 (Box 1)
  Consists of both financial and non-financial correspondence concerning the organization and its operations. This series has circular letters, memorandums, correspondence with other lodges and organizations, and Department of Alcoholic Beverage Control letters and order of suspension. Circular letters and memorandums concern lodge functions, entertainment, fundraising, committees and departments, lodge and organizational publications, member activities, conventions, and the 29th Anniversary celebration held in 1984.
  - Correspondence, 1975-1987 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1987-1991 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Virginia State Department of Alcoholic Beverage Control letters and order of suspension, 1973, 1987-1990, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Financial Records 1972-1991 (Box 1-3)
  Contains audits, bank statements, checks, deed of trust, financial reports, invoices, receipts, tax forms, an organizational budget, stock inventories, and stocks and supplies requistions. Receipts specifically concern building repairs and building operations, beer and food purchases, utilities, cable and telephone service, fire and property insurance, and property, occupational, and alcohol taxes.
  - Bank statements, 1974-1984 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bank statements, 1986-1991 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Beer receipts, 1986-1989 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Building repair receipts and correspondence, 1982-1988 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Burial Fund receipts, 1982-1988 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Cable invoices, 1986-1988 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Checks, 1974, 1988, 1990-1991 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Deed of trust, 1983, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - District Four trustees financial audit, 1981-1983 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Entertainment receipts, 1981-1990 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Fire insurance policy and renewal invoices, 1973-1976 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Florist receipts, 1989-1991 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - House Committee daily financial reports, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - House Committee weekly financial reports, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - House Committee monthly financial reports, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Ice machine rental receipts, 1984-1992 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Internal Revenue Service tax receipts and correspondence, 1975-1976, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Lodge budget, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Lodge income receipts, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Members' receipts, 1980, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous receipts, 1972-1988 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - National Shrine receipts, 1972-1990 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Post office receipts, 1982-1992 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Property tax receipts, 1972-1990 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Property insurance receipts and correspondence, 1985-1990 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Public utility receipts, 1982-1991 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Retail merchants license and check, 1987-1988 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Sales tax worksheets, 1976-1979 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Secretary's Office receipts, 1985-1989 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Secretary's Office six-month reports, 1983, 1987-1989 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Snacks receipts, 1987-1990 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Special occupational tax stamp receipts, 1988-1990 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - State Corporation Commission registration fee receipts and correspondence, 1987-1990 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Stock inventories, requisitions, and disbursements, 1984-1986 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Telephone receipts, 1983-1991 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Virginia Power receipts, 1982-1991 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Treasurer's reports, 1981-1988 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Treasurer's reports, 1988-1990 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Quarterly tax reports, 1981-1992 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous receipts, 1972-1988 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Committee reports and files, 1974-1991 (Box 3-4)
  Consists of correspondence and reports concerning the Athletic, Audit, Beauty, Civil Liberties, Disco, Education, House, and 25th Anniversary Committees, and the Grand Exalted Ruler's Office and the Trustee Board.
  - Antler Guard creed, orders, and correspondence, 1984 and n.d. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Athletic Committee correspondence, 1980-1989 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Audit Committee report, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Beauty Committee correspondence, 1985, 1987 and n.d. (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Bingo Committee permit, correspondence and receipts, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Civil Liberties Committee correspondence, 1982-1989. (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Convention Committee correspondence, 1982-1988 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Disco and Entertainment Committee correspondence, 1982-1988 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - District Deputy and Grand Exalted Ruler quarterly reports, 1982-1992 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Education Committee correspondence, 1982-1991 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Grand Exalted Ruler's National Convention report, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Trustee Board reports, 1976-1989 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - 25th Anniversary Committee memorandums and letters, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Minutes, 1940-1988 (Box 4)
  Comprises the minutes, 1940, 1971 and 1988 of the Greater Capitol City Lodge, minutes, 1975, 1981 and 1984, of the Virginia State Association of the I.B.P.O.E.W., and minutes, 1974, of the Daughters of the I.B.P.O.E.W.
  - Grand Lodge annual meeting minutes, 1940 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Grand Lodge annual meeting minutes, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Grand Lodge annual meeting minutes, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Virginia State Association, I. B. P. O. E. W. annual meeting minutes, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Virginia State Association, I. B. P. O. E. W. annual meeting minutes, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Virginia State Association, I. B. P. O. E. W. annual meeting minutes, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Virginia State Association, Daughters of the I. B. P. O. E. W. annual meeting minutes, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Constitutions, by-laws and charters, 1907-1989 (Box 4-5)
  Specifically contains constitutions and by-laws, 1970, 1979, 1984, 1986, and organizational charters, 1987-1991, for the I. B. P. O. E. W.; a charter, 1907, for the Daughters of I.B.P.O.E.W., Benjamin Temple; a charter, 1956, for Daughters of I.B.P.O.E.W., Daisy Temple; and a charter, 1940, for Brotherhood of Railway and Steamship Clerks.
  - Constitution and by-laws, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Constitution and by-laws, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Constitution and by-laws, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Constitution and by-laws, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Constitution and by-laws recommendations, 1988-1989 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Appointee Club constitution and by-laws, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Ohio Pioneer Department by-laws, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Sharon Baptist Church (Richmond, Virginia) constitution and by-laws, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Lodge operational charters, 1987-1991 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Brotherhood of Railway and Steamship Clerks charter, 1940 (see oversize box 7, folder 3)
  - Daughters of I. B. P. O. E. W., Daisy Temple, charter, 1956 (see oversize box 7, folder 4)
  - Daughters of I. B. P. O. E. W., Benjamin Temple, charter, 1907 (see oversize box 7, folder 5)
- Photographs and posters (Box 5)
  Consists of photographs of the I.B.P.O.E.W. members and building and a poster for the 63rd annual convention of I.B.P.O.E.W.
  - Photographs (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - 63rd annual convention of I. B. P. O. E. W. (see oversize box 7, folder 6)
- Publications 1972-1988 (Box 5)
  This series contains publications consisting of a members' guidebook, annual meeting programs, 1980-1981, a souvenir program, 1972, of the Purple Cross Nurses Division of the I.B.P.O.E.W., a history of the I.B.P.O.E.W., copies of the "Elk Informer" newsletter, 1975-1976, copies of "The Spectrum," 1981-1982, annual convention pamphlets, 1979, 1983, memorial exercise programs, 1978-1988, and newspaper clippings.
  - "Elk Informer" (newsletters), 1975-1976 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - "History of I. B. P. O. E. W." by Charles Wesley n.d. (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - I. B. P. O. E. W. annual convention pamphlets, 1979, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - I. B. P. O. E. W. toast song n.d. (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Jokes and sayings, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Lectures (members' guide book), 1970, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Henry L. Marsh Gala program, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Miscellaneous blank forms n.d. (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - "Elk Informer" (newsletters), 1975-1976 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous events and memorial exercises programs, 1978-1988 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1989 and n.d. (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Purple Cross Nurses Division of the I. B. P. O. E. W. health department, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - "Residential Adaptive Reuse Issues in Virginia," n.d. (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - "The Spectrum," 1981 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - "The Spectrum," 1982 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - 20th Anniversary celebration of the Gospel Baptist Young Adult Choir booklet, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Virginia State Association, I. B. P. O. E. W. annual meeting program, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Virginia State Association, I. B. P. O. E. W. annual meeting program, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Virginia State Association, I. B. P. O. E. W. newsletters, 1984-1991 (Box 5, Folder 26)
- Membership files 195-1992 (Box 6)
  Specifically contains delinquent member lists and notices, membership applications, member burial fund lists, members dues booklets, members dues cards and accounts, member certificates, member name tags, lodges and councils lists, current and former lists of officers, charter member list, membership tests, a lodge list for the Daughters of I.B.P.O.E.W., and membership rolls 1984-1990. There is also members' trial correspondence, duties of unit officers, and correspondence and files pertaining to Scottie Wood.
  - Burial Fund non-participation forms, 1982-1987 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Daisy Temple members list, 1976, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Delinquent member lists, 1981-1990 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Delinquent member notices, 1988-1990 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Duties of unit officers, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Grand Lodge questionnaires, 1975, 1987, 1990 and n.d. (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Grand Lodge former officers, Exalted Rulers, and charter members n.d. (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Thomas Johnson, trial correspondence, 1975, 1986-1988 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Locker rosters, 1975 and n.d. (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Lodges and councils list, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Member applications, 1959, 1962 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Member applications, 1969-1981 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Member Burial Fund lists, 1979, 1985-1986 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Member dues accounts (Baskerville to Nixon), 1961-1969 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Member dues accounts (Oliver to Wyatt), 1961-1969 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Member dues booklets, 1972, 1979 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Member dues cards, 1980-1989 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Member dues cards, 1990-1992 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Member certificates, 1979, 1984-1985 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Member certificates, 1972, 1974, 1981 (see oversize box 7, folder 2)
  - Member list, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Member name tags, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Membership rolls, 1984-1990 (see oversize box 7, folder 1)
  - Membership tests, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Miscellaneous membership files, 1981 and n.d. (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Past Exalted Rulers Appointee Club member list, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Virginia State Association list of officers, 1983 (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Virginia State Association, Daughters of I. B. P. O. E. W. membership roster, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - William Tucker, trial correspondence, 1974-1975, 1984-1989 (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Nuzelle Watson, trial correspondence, 1983-1984 (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - Scottie Wood, trial correspondence, 1986 (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - Scottie Wood, military record, 1962 (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - Scottie Wood, petition, 1981 (Box 6, Folder 31)
  - Scottie Wood, resume, 1980 (Box 6, Folder 32)
  - Scottie Wood, tax returns, 1978-1981 (Box 6, Folder 33)